<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An other sermon preached before the king at Greenewich on Tuesday before Easter, being the 26. of March. 1605. By Anthonie Maxey, Bachelar in Diuinity, and chaplaine to his Maiesty. The points herein handled are these. 1. That there is an hardening. 2. That God hardeneth not. 3. How men become hardened. 4. The meanes to auoid it</title>
            <author>Maxey, Anthony, d. 1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841145</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841145</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07294)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 580:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An other sermon preached before the king at Greenewich on Tuesday before Easter, being the 26. of March. 1605. By Anthonie Maxey, Bachelar in Diuinity, and chaplaine to his Maiesty. The points herein handled are these. 1. That there is an hardening. 2. That God hardeneth not. 3. How men become hardened. 4. The meanes to auoid it</title>
                  <author>Maxey, Anthony, d. 1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Snowdon and Lionell Snowdon, for Clement Knight, and are to be sould at his shoppe, in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Holy Lambe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: Hardening.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5706:1"/>
            <p>AN OTHER SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED BEFORE THE KING AT GREENEWICH ON Tueſday before Eaſter, being the 26. of <hi>March.</hi> 1605.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>ANTHONIE MAXEY, Bachelar in Diuinity, and Chaplaine to his Maieſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The points herein handled are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1.</hi> That there is an Hardening.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2.</hi> That God Hardeneth not.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3.</hi> How men become Hardened.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4.</hi> The meanes to auoid it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PRO. 28.14.</hi>
               </bibl> Bleſſed is the man that feareth alway, but he that Hardeneth his heart ſhall fall into euill.</q>
            <figure>
               <p>IN DO MINO <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ON<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> DO</p>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Snowdon</hi> and <hi>Lionell Snowdon,</hi> for <hi>Clement Knight,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhoppe, in Paules Church-yard, at the Signe of the <hi>Holy Lambe.</hi> 1605.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:5706:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5706:2"/>
            <head>HARDENING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EXOD. 10.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And the Lord hardened <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, and he did not let the children of Iſraell goe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE heart of man is deceitfull and wicked aboue all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>who can know it?</hi> Although the heart of man be ſo little, that it will ſcarce ſerue a Kite for a baite, yet ther are not more windings, nor more turnings in a Maze, or in a Laborinth, then are in the heart of man. The Heathen were ſo forward in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging a diuine power, that rather then they would be without a god, they gaue diuine honour to any kinde of creature.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> worſhipped Idols; the <hi>Perſians</hi> ſtars; the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> plants, and all manner of beaſts; the <hi>Graecians</hi> their owne conceipts, and the <hi>Romanes</hi> made their city a ſhoppe for all kinde of gods. So many were the windings, and ſo infinite the turnings of the heathen touching diuine worſhippe; that <hi>Varro</hi> obſerued in the world thirtie thouſand gods. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute &amp; cunning Atheiſt, he hath a fetch by himſelfe alone, he lets loſe the reines, &amp; followes the ſtreanie of his ſenſual affections, becauſe hee conceiues in his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5706:3"/>heart, and cleane contrarie to the Heathen, ſaith there is no God at all.<note place="margin">Pſal. 14 1.</note> There is a third kinde, who though in ſhow they outwardly acknowledge God, yet they againe haue an other winding, ſecretly to themſelues they plod on, ſwallowing any ſinne, for why?<note place="margin">Zeph. 1, 12.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord will neither doe good nor euill.</hi> Becauſe there is not preſent puniſhment for euerie ſinne. <hi>Tuſh all is well, no harme ſhall happen vnto vs; For God careth not for any thing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 10.12.</note> Laſtly, in theſe our daies, there is yet a fourth ſort, who haue a more ſtrange turning then all the former. For many ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a generall notion of Gods omnipotencie, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and reading ſometimes of Gods <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation</hi> (whereof they vnderſtand no ground, nor conceiue aright) they will preſume to commit any ſinne; for (ſay they) <hi>All is in God, no man can reſiſt his power, if he hath choſen me to life, I am ſure for one, if otherwiſe</hi> (as he did with <hi>Pharao</hi>) hee hath appointed me a <hi>Veſſell of his wrath,</hi> it is not poſſibly to be auoided. Such are the windings, and theſe are the turninges in the heartes, and ſecret thoughts of men, eyther, euerie creature a God, or elſe no God; eyther a God that regardeth not ſinne, or elſe a God that cauſeth vs to ſinne.<note place="margin">Eſay. 29.15.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and deuiſes in the ſight of the Lord, are eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as clay, before the potter.</hi> To conuince the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable errors of the three former, I hold it not conuenient: For, to thinke, there is any one heere preſent, who doth acknowledge no god at all, or ſuch a GOD as regardeth not the actions of men, I hold it wrong to this holy aſſembly, and I hope better things of this Chriſtian audience.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5706:3"/>But to meete with this latter ſort, who leauing all good meanes of their ſaluation, doe inwardly fall away from GOD, and yet in their willfull ignorance would ſhift off, and ſhoue the cauſe of their condemnation vpon God. For ſuch chiefely, haue I vndertaken the expoſition of this Scripture, in opening whereof I will touch theſe foure points. Firſt that there is
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> An Hardening.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> That God Hardeneth not.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> How men become Hardened.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> The meanes to avoid it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt point. There are in the Scriptures two Greeke verbes, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vſed for this <hi>Hardening.</hi> The firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which doth properly ſignifie, to drie vp and wither, vſed often in the 3. to the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> 8.13.15. verſes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Harden not yoour hearts.</hi> The other verbe is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to obdurate, or to make hard. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>They became ſtrangers from the life of God, through the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their hearts.</hi> Hauing thus recourſe vnto the Greeke tongue, we ſhall ſee, that in the heart of man, firſt, there is a drying vp, and a certain withering: For in naturall things, and alſo in the ſoule, as there is a watering which is good and comfortable, ſo there is a drying vp, and withering which is dangerous and hurtfull. In the earth there is a watering, for the hils are the teates, and the ſprings the milke to moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten, and to water the valleyes. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 104. <hi>verſe,</hi> 10. <hi>Hee ſendeth the ſpringes into the riuers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5706:4"/>which runne amongeſt the hilles.</hi> In the earth there is a dryneſſe,<note place="margin">Ioel. 1.20.</note> for (ſaith <hi>Ioell</hi>) <hi>The people mourne for want of moisture, the riuers of waters are dryed vp, and the trees of the field are withered.</hi> In the bodie there is a watering, for the <hi>Liuer</hi> is the ſpring of bloud that runneth into euerie veine, and therefore <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> calleth the <hi>Liuer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ficcleſ. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>The golden well.</hi> In the bodie, there is a withering, for <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth in the Pſalme. 22.15. verſe, <hi>My moiſture is like the drought in Summer, and my bones are dryed vp like a potſhard.</hi> As in the earth and bodie of man, ſo likewiſe in the ſoule, there is a watering and a withering. In the 4. of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> and .14. verſe, there is mention of a <hi>well of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing waters for the ſoule:</hi> The preaching of grace in Chriſt is called the <hi>watering of Apollo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.6.</note> The prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Eſay. 12.3.</note> 
               <hi>with ioy ye ſhall draw waters out of the welles of ſaluation.</hi> Contrariwiſe, where this grace doth not water,<note place="margin">Greg. mag.</note> there is withering. <hi>Si ſpiritus irrigatio defuerit, omnis plantatio exareſcit.</hi> Euery planting that hath not the watering of Gods ſpirit, it withereth and dryes away: therefore ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt, the godly, they are like the tree panted by the riuers ſide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> there is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering: <hi>but the vngodly are as a Garden that hath no water, and as the broken leafe that fadeth,</hi> there is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering.<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The other Greeke verbe is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies to harden. There bee <hi>Phiſicae &amp; aethicae viciſsitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines,</hi> there is a naturall and a ſpirituall Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie. In the naturall courſe of thinges, there is a congealing and an hatdening,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.30.31.</note> as of the yce and froſt, which <hi>Iob</hi> verie fitly calleth <hi>the bands of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion:</hi> becauſe by the cold Eaſt and North windes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5706:4"/>the water becomes as a ſtone, and the clods are bound together. Contrarie to this <hi>Haraening,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 147.18.</note> there is a melting: <hi>Hee ſendeth out his word, and melteth them.</hi> As when the froſt doth giue, and the ſhowers fall, which <hi>Iob</hi> calles in the ſame place, <hi>The ſweet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſluence of Pleiades.</hi> Both in nature, and in the ſoule alſo, there is a <hi>Reſoluing,</hi> and a <hi>Hardening: Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. The word is called <hi>Dewe,</hi> and there is a thaw or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall melting, when the heauenly dewe doth cauſe the ſoule to giue, and to reſolue into teares of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: ſo in the 2. of <hi>Kings.</hi> 22.10. <hi>Ioſias heart did melt, when he heard the law read.</hi> When King <hi>Dauid</hi> had committed murder and adultery, very grieuous ſinnes; he neuer be thought himſelfe of the matter, but begann to congeale, and to be <hi>Hardened</hi> in his ſinne, but aſſoone as the prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> had awaked him, and his heart (like <hi>Gedeons fleece</hi>) had drunck vp the heauenly dew, then preſently <hi>Dauid</hi> began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, his ſoule melted with ſorrow, and as appeareth in the 51. <hi>Pſal,</hi> he reſolued into teares of Repentance. <hi>Hezechias,</hi> when God had giuen vnto him a ſodaino and triumphant victory ouer the hoſt of <hi>Zenacharib;</hi> preſently after, in the pride of his hart, he forgat God and began to congeale in ſinne: but aſſoone as the word of the Lord came vnto him by the prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> then preſently his heart melted, the bloud of his ſoule flowed forth in his repentant teares, as appeareth in the 38 of <hi>Eſay: he turned his face vnto the wall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 38.3.</note> 
               <hi>and wept bitterly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, as there is a <hi>Melting,</hi> ſo alſo there is an <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening</hi> in the ſoule, and that is, when the cuſtome of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:5706:5"/>ſinne hath beaten ſuch an hard tracke, and ſo tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled the ſoule, that the word of God (the ſeede of life) cannot enter. This is expreſſed in the 13. of Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi> by the parable of the ſeede which fell by the high way ſide, where there was ſuch an hard way, ſuch a beaten path made by the common en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of ſinne, that the ſeede could take no roote, but the diuell comes like an <hi>Harpie,</hi> and deuoureth it, before it can enter: For example heereof, we will take <hi>Cain,</hi> and King <hi>Pharao,</hi> whom my Text concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: <hi>Cain</hi> hauing ſlaine his brother <hi>Abell,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted horrible murder: the word of the Lord came vnto him, ſaying: <hi>Where is thy brother Abell?</hi> did <hi>Cains</hi> heart relent? did he confeſſe and ſay, I haue finned? or did he reſolue into teares with <hi>Dauid?</hi> no ſuch matter: but firſt he anſwered with a foule word: <hi>I cannot tell where he is:</hi> then he diſpiſed the Lord to his face, as if he ſhould ſay, you may goe looke him, <hi>am I my brothers keeper?</hi> marke but this anſwer of <hi>Cain,</hi> and his cariage therein, and you neede no other example of an heart that is <hi>Hardened:</hi> neyther affection in kinred could touch him, nor ſhame of the world check him, nor the bloud of his ſlaine brother moue him, nor the glorious preſence of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh him, nor the guilt of his owne thoughts raſe him, nor (at laſt) the quickning word of God, which is powreful to raiſe the very dead; none of theſe could any whit reuiue him. <hi>Triplex circa praecordia ferrum,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith of <hi>Leuiatha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orat. Tob. <hi>41.15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>his heart was harder then the nether milſtone, Pharao,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the word of God came vnto him by <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pharao.</note> he was ſo far from yeilding, that he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5706:5"/>ſeemed preſently as though he would haue fought with GOD: <hi>Who is the Lord, I know no Lord, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I let Iſraell goe.</hi> And whereas the word, and miracles ioyned with that word were ſufficient to conuince any liuing: <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart was ſo ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that though by a ſtrange miracle, al the water in the land were become bloud, and did ſauour moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holſomely, yet it is ſaid, <hi>Pharao went home,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and all this could not enter into his heart,</hi> it could not pierce him. When the Prophet cried to the Altar of <hi>Ieroboam, O Altar, Altar,</hi> heare the word of the Lord: <hi>the Altar heard, and elaue a ſunder.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kina 3.</note> But the word of God which in <hi>Ieremie.</hi> 23.29. is called an <hi>Hammer,</hi> becauſe it bruiſeth the ſtonie hearts of men, this <hi>Hammer</hi> with tenne miracles gaue tenne mightie ſtrokes at <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ohs</hi> heart, and yet it could neuer bruiſe it.</p>
            <p>Thus we may plainely ſee, there is a <hi>watering</hi> by grace, and a <hi>meiting</hi> by Gods word, as appeareth by <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> who reſolued into teares: againe through want of grace, there is a <hi>withering,</hi> and by cuſtome of ſinne there is an <hi>Hardening,</hi> as in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Pharao,</hi> whoſe hearts the word of God could not pierce, but the more they were beaten on, the more hard and flintie they became.</p>
            <p>It remaineth in the ſecond point to diſcuſſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this <hi>Hardening</hi> be of God. In opening whereof it is ſtrange to heare how vntruly, how vncharitably we are charged by our aduerſaries, not onely <hi>Campion</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> but eſpecially in certaine ARTICLES or <hi>Forcible Reaſons</hi> lately publiſhed, wherein it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly ſet downe, that the Proteſtants doe make God
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5706:6"/>
               <hi>the author and onely cauſe of ſinne,</hi> that deride <hi>Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Artic. 5.</note> and plainly affirme, <hi>God is worſe then the diuell, and ſo are bound in conſcience neuer to aske God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of their ſinnes.</hi> Oh fearefull blaſphemie, and wordes vnſeemely Chriſtian eares: Where is Modeſtie? where is truth and Chriſtian pietie? Is this our doctrine? doe we thus teach? no verely: both in word and writing we acknowledge the Lord our GOD to be full of compaſſion and loue, the bowels of his mercieſweete and amiable; he would not the death of any, he is gratious and kinde, gentle and readie to forgiue, and (to the death) we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, more then moſt holy, pure and iuſt are all his workes and waies: therefore the Lord be iudge betweene them and vs, and lay not this ſinne vnto their charge.</p>
            <p>Touching this doctrine, how ſinne firſt came to be, how it came in, where it firſt tooke beginning, and that GOD is not the author of it, I haue ſhewed heeretoſore in handling the <hi>Golden Chaine,</hi> the meanes of our ſaluation: namely, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell was <hi>Primitiuus peccator,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> the firſt offender: from him ſinne firſt boyleth vp, as out of the maine Sea; from Sathan when it comes to <hi>Adam,</hi> it ariſeth as out of a Spring; from this Spring it is reſerued in nature as in a Conduit; from nature conueyed to concupiſcence (as by a pipe), and from thence doth flow all the miſchiefe and wickedneſſe that is in the life of man. Well then: if ſinne doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from the ſuggeſtion of Sathan woorking through our owne coucupiſcence; and ſo GOD
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5706:6"/>wholly freed from all imputation of euill: why is it ſo often ſaid in the Scripture. <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.30. <hi>And the Lord hardened the heart of</hi> Sihon <hi>King of</hi> Heſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, <hi>and made him obſtinate:</hi> Ioſhua <hi>the</hi> 11.20. <hi>It came of the Lord to harden their hearts:</hi> and heere of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of <hi>Exodus, and the Lord hardened the heart of</hi> Pharao. To make this plaine: it is a poynt well knowne vnto the learned, that this ſpeech (where it is ſaid) <hi>God Hardened:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Flaccus. Illiricus. <hi>P. Lomb. li.</hi> 1. <hi>diſt.</hi> 41.</note> the Hebrue Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect doth ſignifie a permiſſion, and not an action. Verbes that ſignifie to doe, they often expreſſe a ſuffering and not a doing. <hi>Deſtruit cum deſerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The. Aquin. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1.</hi> q. <hi>23.</hi> arti, <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> God is then ſaid to <hi>Harden,</hi> when he doth forſake. <hi>Impios cum non retrabit a malo culpae, dicitur dimittere.</hi> As the enduing with grace is the effect of Gods <hi>Election,</hi> ſo the withholding of his grace is the effect of <hi>Reprobation. Dei includere eſt clauſis non aperire,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> vpon the 12. of <hi>Iob.</hi> and four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene verſe. Euerie action hath his quality from the roote of the affection, and from the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Author: Deus autem (quoad peceatum) non habet poſitiue velle, ſed tantum priuatiue,</hi> Touching ſinne, God hath no <hi>Poſitiue</hi> will, but onely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of former ſinnes a <hi>Priuation</hi> of his grace. To be ſhort: God doth <hi>Harden,</hi> as Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith: <hi>Non malum obtrudendo, ſed gratiam non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedendo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> not by cauſing vs to commit ſinne, but by not granting vnto vs his grace. I, but how comes it to paſſe, that we (aſwell as others) are not partakers of Gods grace? why haue not wee alſo his good Spirit to direct and guide vs? Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> makes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5706:7"/>it plaine againe.<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Non idcò non habet home gratiam, quia Deus non dat, ſed quià home non aceipit:</hi> men become <hi>Hardened,</hi> and want the ſpirit of grace, why? not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe GOD doth not offer it vnto them, but becauſe they receiue it not, when it is offered. For example: One of vs being ſicke, and like to dye, the Phyſicion knowing our caſe, hee takes with him ſome preſeruatiue to comfort vs, and comes to the doore and knocks; if we will not, or bee not able to let him in, wee periſh and dye, and the cauſe is not in the Phyſicion, but in our ſelues that let him not in.<note place="margin">Plato de leg. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Sinne is a diſeaſe, whereof wee are all ſick, for wee haue all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: <hi>Romanes.</hi> 6.12. verſe. Chriſt, hee is the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of our ſoules:<note place="margin">Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in Mat. <hi>9.12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Venit de coelo magnus medicus, quia per totum vbique iacebit aegretus.</hi> Chriſt the great Phiſition came downe from heauen, becauſe all mankind was generally infected. He comes to the dore of our hearts, and there hee knockes. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.35.</note> 
               <hi>I ſtand at the dore and knocke,</hi> Hee bringeth with him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the bread of life, his eternall word to comfort vs, if wee let him in, if wee open the doore of our hearts,<note place="margin">Lue. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> he will come in, and ſuppe with vs, as hee did with <hi>Mary,</hi> and forgiue vs all our ſinnes; but if wee will not, or through long contagion of our ſinne bee not able to let Chriſt in, wee dye in our ſinnes, and the caſe is euident, not becauſe Chriſt doth not offer grace, and comfort vnto vs, but becauſe wee receiue it not, when it is offered. <hi>Merito perit aegretus qui non medicum vocat, ſed vltro venientem reſpuit,</hi> worthily doth that ſicke patient periſh,<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſculus.</note> who will neither ſend for the Phyſicion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5706:7"/>himſelfe, nor accept of his helpe, when it is offered.</p>
            <p>More plainely thus, in the 14. of Saint <hi>Mathew.</hi> Our Sauiour walking on the ſea, hee badde Saint <hi>Peter</hi> come vnto him, who walking on the water, ſeeing ſtorme and tempeſt ariſe, his heart failed, and hee beganne to ſinck, vppon his cry vnto our Sauiour, hee preſently ſtretched forth his hand, tooke him into the ſhipp, and ſaued him. This world (wee know by dayly experience) it is a ſea of trouble and miſery: our Sauiour (as he ſaid to Saint <hi>Peeter</hi>) ſo moſt louingly hee willeth euery one of vs to come vnto him: as wee walke, ſtormes and tempeſts doe ariſe, through frailty of our fleſh, and the weaknes of our faith, wee beginn to ſinck, our Sauiour, he ſtretcheth forth his hand, hee giueth vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> his <hi>worde,</hi> his <hi>Sacramentes,</hi> the good moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones of his Spirit, to ſaue vs from ſincking, and to keepe vs in the ſhipp of his Church: if we refuſe theſe meanes, wee periſh, wee ſinck in our ſinnes, why? not becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth not moſt kindly put forth his hand vnto vs, but bicauſe in want and diſtreſſe wee lay not hold vppon him. <hi>This is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, that light is come into the world, men refuſe it, and loue darknes more then light.</hi> Our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour with great louing kindneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.18.</note> hee doth inuite all men to his <hi>Great Supper,</hi> if we make excuſes, or wilfully refuſe to come, hee may iuſtly pronounce, <hi>none of thoſe that were bidden ſhall euer taſte of my ſupper.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lue.</hi> 14.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore lett not men deceiue themſelues, and complaine as though God did <hi>harden</hi> their hearts
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5706:8"/>and denye them grace and mercie, for as <hi>Ionas</hi> ſaith in his 2. Chapter,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.8.</note> and 8. verſe. <hi>They forſake their owne mercie. Deus prior in amore,</hi> God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hateth vntill hee be firſt hated, and ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with Saint <hi>Ambroſe: Nemo tibi Chriſtum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt auferre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ.</note> 
               <hi>niſi te illi auferas,</hi> no man can ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Chriſt from thee, except firſt thou doeſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thy ſelfe from him. This is plainely to be obſerued in <hi>Pharao,</hi> had he (being long before peac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ſetled in a rich and mighty Kingdome) made right vſe of the bleſſings of GOD, had hee at the firſt, or often-times after, yeilded vnto the word of the Lord, he had neuer come to the ſtate of <hi>Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge,</hi> nor left himſelfe ſuch a fearefull ſpectacle of Gods wrath for euer. But <hi>Pharao,</hi> feeling welth and reuenew coming in ſo faſt and aboundantly, that he builded new Citties (<hi>Pithom</hi> and <hi>Raamſes</hi>) to lay vp his treaſures,<note place="margin">Exod. 1.11.</note> his heart was ſo bent and ſet vpon couetouſneſſe (ſuch multitudes of people moyling and labouringe in ſundry workes for his profitte) that in no caſe hee could endure to heare of their departure.<note place="margin">Exod 5.2. Chap. 7.11.</note> Firſt, he ſaid flatly, they ſhould not goe; Secondly, hee ſought to ſhift off the matter, affirming the miracles not to bee done by Gods hand, but by enchantment; Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">8.25.</note> hee yeilded they ſhould offer ſacrifice, but onely in his owne land; Fourthly, hee was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they ſhould goe ſacrifice out of his land (but ſtill he would condition with God) <hi>None but the men ſhould goe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">10.11.</note> Fiftly, the men ſhould goe, the women goe,<note place="margin">10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the children goe, but their ſheepe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5706:8"/>and Oxen (wherein their wealth ſtoode) ſhould not goe.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Pharao</hi> (through a wretched and griple minde) neuer left winding and turning, dallying and preſuming of the Lordes mercy, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, till adding one ſinne vnto another, his heart became <hi>Hardened:</hi> Nay,<note place="margin">Obſerue heere how fearefull a thing it is, wilfully to ſinne againſt our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> notwithſtanding ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miracles, and that before he confeſſed the <hi>Lord</hi> to be <hi>God, hee and his people ſinfull,</hi> and earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Moſes</hi> to pray for him, yet contrarie to his owne thoughts, and againſt his owne knowledge, when he ſaw the people of Iſraell were gone, he flies to ſtrength of warre, he calles his Captaines, he mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters his people, he gathers his Chariots, he purſues with all might and maine, till at laſt both he and his (ouer whelmed in the ſea) receiued the fearefull and finall iudgement of wilfull diſobedience. Now then let all the earth know the goodneſſe of the Lord, and wiſely obſerue his loue vnto mankinde for euer. It is true, <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart was <hi>Hardened,</hi> and he with his Nobles vtterly ouerthrowne. But before this ouerthrow, all meanes poſſibly that could be, were vſed to winne <hi>Pharao.</hi> Bleſſing vpon bleſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receiued; puniſhment vpon puniſhment af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inflicted; <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtill and againe prayed for him; <hi>Aaron</hi> euer and anon perſwaded him; the plagues to aſtoniſh him, were ſodaine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding wonderfull; the deliuerance, to winne him, was preſent, and more miraculous: the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters</hi> confeſſed, the <hi>People</hi> cried out, his <hi>Seruants</hi> were offended, <hi>Aegypt</hi> was almoſt quite deſtroyed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5706:9"/>the land of <hi>Goſhen</hi> was ſtill vntouched; God againe, and againe, and ſtill againe was entreated, and yet <hi>Pharao</hi> remained obſtinate. Shall we then ſay that God <hi>Hardened Pharaohs</hi> heart? Be it farre from vs: for it is directly ſet down in the 9. chap. 34. verſe. <hi>And when Pharao ſaw the haile and thunder were gone, he ſinned againe, and Hardened his heart;</hi> and againe the 8. chap. 15. verſe. <hi>When</hi> Pharao <hi>ſaw that he had reſt, he hardened his owne heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, I would to God it were onely <hi>Pharaohs</hi> caſe, and that we alſo being Chriſtians did not abuſe the long forbearance, and much louing kindneſſe of our God. For, now feare of the ſtorme is ouer, but euen one yeare or two: now that our louing God through his vnſpeakeable mercie hath ſo ſweetly ſet all in order,<note place="margin">Behold our vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes to God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and peaceable a Prince.</note> that all Nations round about vs ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, now that he hath ſetled amongſt vs a moſt happie and religious peace; now that he gath giuen honor, plentie, and reſt throughout all the land; ſtill, ſtill we dally and trifle with the Lord, according to our priuate humors, and ſeuerall ſectes; we will not proſeſſe the Goſpell, except we firſt condition (as <hi>Pharao</hi> did) both with our God and King: with hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearts we do not ſubmit our ſelues peaceably to ſerue the Lord: For this bleſſed <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> our ſoules flame not with thankefull loue, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as they ought) breake foorth into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting prayſes: Nay, whereas the word of GOD came tenne times to <hi>Pharao,</hi> willing him to let the people of Iſraell goe, and ſerue the Lord, the ſame word comes an hundred times tenne to our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5706:9"/>heartes, crying and beating vpon vs to haue vs let goe our contentions, our carnall and peruerſe affections, and yet wee neuer relente at the ſame. <hi>A mans heart will tell him more then ſeuen watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in a Tower:</hi> Wee know,<note place="margin">Ecceus. <hi>37.14.</hi>
               </note> we know (euery one in his owne boſome) the ſinnes, which we ſecretly foſter, and will not let goe. But as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> exhorteth the Iewes, <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 3.12. ſo I aduiſe you in the name of GOD. <hi>Take heed, take heed, leaſt in any of you there bee found a falſe and an euill heart, to depart from the liuing GOD.</hi> For aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is a fearefull and bitter thing to carye euer a ſelfe-wild and peruerſe minde, to reſpect meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the applauſe of men, and fading pleaſures of this life; ſo, inwardly falling away from God, and loſing the bleſſed comfort of our ſaluation. O Sauiour ſweet, and ſecret hope, turne vs, that we may be turned; bow our heartes, and the heartes of our ſeede vnto thee, that we may feare thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, acknowledge thy goodneſſe, and ſtand faſt in thy loue for euer.</p>
            <p>The third poynt is to ſhow how men become <hi>Hardened;</hi> in opening whereof, wee are to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there are three ſortes of <hi>Hardening: Naturalis, Voluntaria, Hidicialis.</hi> The firſt is by <hi>Nature,</hi> the ſecond by <hi>Habite</hi> and <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> the third by the <hi>Iuſt iudgement of GOD.</hi> The firſt is the forgetfulneſſe or dulneſſe in a naturall man, when hee ouerſhootes himſelfe, for want of wiſe obſeruation and remembrance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:5706:10"/>In this ſixth of <hi>Marke,</hi> our Sauiour Chriſt fed fiue thouſand men with fiue loaues,<note place="margin">Mark. 6.</note> and two fiſhes, a miracle ſufficient to prooue vnto his Diſciples, that he was the Sonne of GOD. Yet preſently after, when he came walking on the Sea, and cauſed the winde to ceaſe, they ſtoode ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and did not acknowledge his <hi>Diuinitie:</hi> for (ſaith the Scripture) in the two and fifteth verſe.<note place="margin">Gods children may be blinded in mind, and hardened in heart for a time</note> They conſidered not the miracle of the loaues, becauſe <hi>their hearts were Hardened,</hi> that is, through naturall imperfection they had for got it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is an <hi>Hardening</hi> by <hi>habit,</hi> when (through a careleſſe ſecuritie) men doe continue in ſinne, and take ſuch a cuſtome, as they can hardly leaue. So <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> his heart by cuſtome was ſo long bent, and ſet vpon couetouſneſſe, that being conuerſant amongeſt the Apoſtles, and daily imployed in moſt diuine and holy actions. Yet euen then, his minde and thought ſtill ranne vpon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, vpon gaine. This is <hi>Habitualis obduratio,</hi> an <hi>Hardening</hi> which growes, by continuance in ſinne. He that is in this caſe, it ſtandes him vpon to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp his ſpirits, and ſtrongly to reſiſt ſinne, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter himſelfe oſt-times vnto deuout and priuate Meditations, to ioy in hearing the word, with reuerence to receiue the bleſſed Sacramentes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to bee feruent in prayer, for ſo Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> willed <hi>Simon Magus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 8.22.</note> 
               <hi>Repent and pray, that (if it bee poſsible) the thoughtes of thy heart may bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5706:10"/>The third and laſt is <hi>Iudicialis obduratis, an Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which proceedes from the iuſt iudgemente of God. Cumpeccatum fit paenapeccati,</hi> when ſinne becomes a puniſhment to him that committeth it,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.2.7.</note> as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a recompence of former errors; when the thought is ſo poyſoned, the minde and ſoule ſo generally infected, that the ſpirit of God is vtterly quenched: no light of nature, no priuate counſell, no publicke exhortation out of the worde, no inwarde motions of Gods ſpirite can preuaile, but he goeth on ſo long, and is ſo farre ſpent, that beeing paſt all feare to offend, careleſlye hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no ſcruple of any ſinne whatſoeuer; till at length finding in himſelfe no hope of recouery, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God ſtrikes him apparantly with his iudgement, as hee did <hi>Pharao;</hi> or elſe by his death hee paſſeth ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to the graue without repentance, as <hi>Diues;</hi> or in this life (as <hi>Iudas</hi> did) doeth plunge himſelfe in the gulfe of deſperation. This is that <hi>Hardening</hi> which is heere meant of <hi>Pharao.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Hardening</hi> is not all on a ſuddaine: <hi>Non rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus primo impetu vt Deo reluctemur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calw.</note> no man is <hi>Harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> at the firſt. <hi>Nemo fit repente miſer. Hebr.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Take heede leaſt anie of you be Hardened through the deceiteful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>deceitfulneſſe of ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Aquin.</note> it creepeth like a canker worme, it gathers, it ſteales vpon vs, and ſo vnder the foreknowledge of God, men come vnto <hi>Hardening</hi> by degrees. <hi>Naturalis eſt ordo, vt ab imperfecto, ad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum quis moueatur,</hi> It is a naturall courſe euen in euill (ſayeth the ſchooleman) by degrees to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5706:11"/>to perfection.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7.</note> 
               <hi>As they that dwellin Gods houſe, will bring foorth more fruite, and then appeare before the God of gods in perfect beauty:</hi> ſo, on the contrary, the wicked are not <hi>Hardened</hi> all at once, but as they offende more and more, ſo by little and little they grow to the height of ſinne, and they <hi>doe fall from one miſchiefe to an other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudas</hi> was firſt a cunning <hi>Diſſembler;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat, 26.8. Ioh. 12.5, Mat. 26.25.48. Mat. 27.5.</note> ſecondly, he became a ſecret <hi>Thiefe;</hi> thirdly, he grew to bee an impudent <hi>Lyar;</hi> fourthly, he proued a bold <hi>Traitor;</hi> laſtly, a deſperate <hi>Reprobate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diſeaſes of the bodie, they do not grow at one and the ſelfe-ſame time, they do firſt appeare but by riot and deſtemperature vſed long before ſo the ſoule infected with vncleane thoughtes, and in youth accuſtomed to euill actions, at length commeth to the vncurable diſeaſe of <hi>Hardening.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug confeſſ. 8</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the 8. of his <hi>Confeſſ.</hi> doth open this point verie plainely.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> the diuell by concupiſcence ſuggeſteth euill thoughts; euill thoughts egge on delight; delight towleth on conſent; conſent engendereth action; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bringeth forth cuſtome; cuſtome groweth to neceſſitie; and neceſſity in ſinning is the forerunner of death. For example. Firſt, the diuell ſuggeſteth euill thoughts, ſo he did vnto <hi>Eue,</hi> he wound her in by tainting her thought, by telling her, ſhe ſhould haue <hi>all knowledge, and be as GOD:</hi> this euill thought egged on delight; for as appeareth in the ſixth verſe, the Apple grew pleaſant in her eyes; this delight towled on conſent, for then ſhee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5706:11"/>tooke of the <hi>fruite,</hi> laſtly of conſent came the action, for ſhee did eate and gaue it to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            <p>Now, when the action of ſinne is committed, there doth not preſently follow <hi>Hardening:</hi> for, if the heart doe melt and thaw, if the ſoule doe giue and reſolue into teares of repentance for the ſame, then there is no <hi>Hardening.</hi> But, if from one action com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, wee come vnto another, and ſo to the cuſtome and continuance in ſinne, then are wee ſnared with the cordes of our owne iniquity, and fettered with this chaine againſt the generall day of Gods Iudgment. To make this plaine, I will ſhow you by ſeauen degrees, as it were by ſeuen ſtayres, how men do diſcend into this pit of <hi>Hardening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſtep is <hi>importable: Sinne</hi> at the firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> it is importable, it ſeemes vntollerable to be borne.<note place="margin">Importabile.</note> One that hath beene religiouſly brought vp, hath beene accuſtomed to a milde and honeſt conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and hath bene fearefull to offend; at length, if through bad company, through his owne weaknes, and the allurements of Sathan, he falleth into any foule ſinne; at the firſt it is importable, it doth ſtrike ſuch an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror into him, that he is in a wofull taking and grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly tormented. This wee may ſee by <hi>Dauid,</hi> who hauing alwaies a tender conſcience, loath to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, yet after ouer taken by committing murder and adultery, aſſoone as he ſaw what he had done, he was mightely troubled, wherſoeuer he became, his offence ſo ſtuck in his thought, that in the 51 <hi>Pſal:</hi> 3. he cryeth out, <hi>my ſinne is euer before me, it is continually in my ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5706:12"/>The <hi>ſecond</hi> ſtayer is <hi>Graue,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>heauie:</hi> for ſinne being committed twiſe or thrice,<note place="margin">Graue.</note> it is not as it was at the firſt importable, but it is heauie. Hee ſorrowes, and is grieued, but hee is nothing ſo troubled in minde, nor afflicted in conſcience as hee was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third</hi> ſtayer is <hi>Leue;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>light:</hi> For hee that hath v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe more often to ſinne: that which at the firſt was importable, and afterwardes heauie, at length becommeth light. This appeareth by the vnchaſte woman ſpoken off in the Prouerbes, who hauing had ſome practiſe in ſinne, ſhe makes no more matter of it, but lightly paſſeth it ouer with <hi>wiping her mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 30-20.</note> and ſaith <hi>ſhe hath not ſinned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth</hi> ſtayer is <hi>inſenſibile,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> for after that ſinnne bee made light of,<note place="margin">Enſenſibile.</note> and that there bee no remorſe nor griefe for ſinne, then they grow paſt feeling: ſuch were the Iſraelites of whome the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeaketh in his 5. chapter and 3. verſe: <hi>Thou haſt ſmitten them, but they haue not ſorrowed, for they haue made their faces harder then a ſtone,</hi> that is, they haue ſinned ſo long, that now they are paſt feeling.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fift</hi> ſtaire is <hi>Delectabile.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> When men take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in ſinne (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>They reioyce in doing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and delight in wickedneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Delectabile.</note> Hereof Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Tumeſt conſummata infoelicitas, vbiturpia non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum committuntur, ſedetiam delectant:</hi> Then is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of condemnation certaine, when ſoule ſinnes are not onely committed,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> but are delightfull alſo.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſixt</hi> ſtayre is <hi>Deſiderabile,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deſiderabile.</note> when (through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5706:12"/>men growe to ſuch a cuſtome, that they inwardly deſire to ſinne, ſo that as Saint <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> ſaid: <hi>Si nunquam moreretur, nunquam vellepce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care deſineret:</hi> ſuch a man, if he ſhould neuer die, hee would neuer ceaſe to ſinne, for though he did not commit it in action, yet ſtill he would deſire it in thought.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſeauenth</hi> ſtayre is <hi>defenſibile. When he hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a forehead of braſſe. Eſay.</hi> 48.4.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith) when the tyrant doth boaſt that he can doe miſcheif, <hi>when he ſits in the ſeate of the ſcorner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Defenſibile. Pſai. <hi>1.1.</hi>
               </note> when he doth not only by habyt deſire to ſinne, and delight in it, but now he will take vpon him to defend it. <hi>Peccatum porta mortis, defenſio eſt limen inferni,</hi> Sinne is the high way to death,<note place="margin">Origen.</note> but the defence of ſinne is the very next ſteppe into hell, at this point were the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who being reproued for idolatry, <hi>the Scripture ſaith,</hi> they ſaide <hi>deſperatly,</hi> wee haue <hi>loued ſtrange gods, and them will wee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low againe; they refuſed to hearken and pulled away the ſhoulder, and ſtopped their cares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zacha. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>and made their hearts as an Adamant ſtone.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.3.</note> 
               <hi>Impius cum venerit in profundum contemnit,</hi> a diſſolute liuer once growne to the height of ſinne, becomes deſperate.</p>
            <p>Thus ſinne, firſt it is <hi>importable,</hi> ſecondly <hi>Heauy,</hi> thirdly it becomes <hi>Light,</hi> fourthly <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>delightfull,</hi> ſixtly <hi>deſired,</hi> and laſtly to be <hi>defended.</hi> heere is <hi>deſcenſus auerni,</hi> theſe be the ſtayers that leade to the chambers of death, and the ſteppes, wherby the reprobate do deſcend vnto finall deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Indeede, at the firſt, when ſinne is <hi>importable,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5706:13"/>that we are wonderfully grieued for committing of it, there is great hope of recouerie, and he that ſo feeling the wound of ſinne, doth there ſtay the courſe of it, it is an excellent ſigne of ſaluation: <hi>Initiune ſalutis notitia peccati,</hi> the firſt ſteppe of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is the firſt finding out, and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne. In the ſecond of the <hi>Actes,</hi> when they ſawe and knew their ſinne, they cryed out, <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall wee doe to be ſaued:</hi> this horror, this troubled minde, it made them ſeeke for comfort, and ſo brought them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when ſinne is a burden vnto our ſoules, ſo that we would faine be eaſed of it, there is yet good hope: we may ſee it by <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 38. Pſalm. 4. verſ. <hi>Mine iniquities are gone ouer mine head, and are as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den too heauie for me to beare:</hi> the weight of this burden made <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 18. verſe following, <hi>to confeſſe his wickedneſſe, and to be ſory for his ſinne,</hi> it made him flie vnto God for eaſe: <hi>O caſt your burden vpon the Lord, for he will not ſuffer the righteous to fall for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, when men make light of ſinne, ſurely danger is not farre off, <hi>for a threefold cord is not eaſily broken, and the third letting of bloud in the ſame veine is exceeding dangerous:</hi> but yet ſtill there is ſome hope, for though in the hot chaſe of our blinde and youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſires, though then for a time we account it a light matter, to commit this or that ſinne, yet God may touch our heartes, <hi>Chriſt may looke backe vpon vs, as he did on S.</hi> Peter, <hi>who denyed him thrice,</hi> his word may ſo ſtrike vs, that we may come to know our ſelues, to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:5706:13"/>ſee in what caſe we are, to bewaile our infirmitie, and ſo turne vnto God by prayer and repentance:<note place="margin">Iob. 33.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>All theſe things</hi> (as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith) <hi>will God worke twice or thrice with a man.</hi> But if we come to <hi>(inſenſibile)</hi> to the fourth ſtayre, ſo that we grow <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> we ſinne dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and haue no ſenſe of it, if there be no remorſe, no griefe nor diſlike of ſinne; wo be vnto vs, 2. <hi>Amos.</hi> 6. <hi>For three tranſgreſsions, and for foure, I will not turne to Iſraell</hi> (ſaith the Lord), without the infinite and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary mercie of God, we are the ſonnes of wrath, for then followeth this deadly wound of <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening.</hi> It is a principle in Phiſicke, <hi>grauiſsime is aegro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, qui ſe non ſentit aegrotare,</hi> if a man be ſicke, and know it not, out of queſtion, he is very dangerouſly and deadly ſicke; he that findes in himſelfe no want of any thing (as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicea</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I ſtand not in neede of any thing. This deadneſſe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.17.</note> this vn-feeling numneſſe, it is a plaine foreteller of death: for example, if a man haue taken a grieuous wound in his bodie, if it ake, if it pricke and ſhoote, if it paine him, eyther it is healing, or elſe there is hope to heale it: but (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) <hi>Quod non dolet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>non proſano, ſed promortuo computandum,</hi> if the wound be ſuch, that it neuer cauſeth griefe, if it neuer ake nor ſmart, vndoubtedly it is dead fleſh, of neceſſitie it muſt be cut off.</p>
            <p>To commit actuall and preſumptuous ſinnes, when a mans owne knowledge and Gods Spirit cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in him to the contrarie, theſe are woundes, and grieuous woundes vnto the ſoule, and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath gone on ſo farre, that he doth delight
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5706:14"/>in theſe ſinnes, ſo often, ſo long, that his minde is neuer troubled, his thoughtes neuer checked, his ſoule neuer grieued, ſurely ſuch a one (being vtterly <hi>paſt feeling</hi>) is very neere to this fearefull eſtate of <hi>Hardening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeede the Scripture ſaith, <hi>At what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſinne, from the bottome of his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>God will put all his wickedneſſe out of his remembrance.</hi> Whereupon many take their pleaſure in ſinne, and go diſſolutely on, thinking at laſt to make all good by repentance. It is true, if they can repent. But they muſt obſerue what Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith. <hi>Qui promittit poenitenti veniam, non promittit peccanti pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nitentiam</hi> God who promiſeth to euerie one that repenteth, forgiueneſſe; doth not promiſe to euery one that ſinneth, repentance.</p>
            <p>Repentance is the gift of God, and ſuch as are <hi>Hardened</hi> (becauſe in times paſt they haue deſpiſed the riches of his bountie &amp; grace, his long ſuffering and mercie which did call them to repentance) when they would, they cannot repent. <hi>After Hardneſſe the heart it can not repent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The holy and bleſſed <hi>Sacramentes</hi> now preſently to bee adminiſtred, they are <hi>Pledges</hi> of Gods loue, and <hi>Seales</hi> of our ſaluation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</note> By Baptiſme, <hi>he brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the heades of the Dragons in the waters, Et per Baptiſmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coeli <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anua aperitur,</hi> By Baptiſm eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doore of heauen is ſet open. The Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, it is, <hi>canalis gratiae, &amp; lauacrum animae,</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit of Grace, and the bath of the Soule. What can be more ioyfull, then by receiuing the ſigne of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5706:14"/>croſſe to fight vnder the banner of Chriſtes loue, and to bee knit into the miſticall body of his <hi>Saints.</hi> What can bee more ioyfull, then to receiue that pure and Princely bloud, the leaſt drop whereof being able to redeeme a thouſand worlds, I may reſt aſſured, it is a full and perfect ſatisfaction for all my ſinnes: ſo that, if my bodie hath ſinned, his bodie hath made a mendes: if my ſoule hath ſinned, his ſoule hath made a recompence: and therefore both ſoule and bodie are his, and ſo we firmely and fully ſeated in a Chriſtian ioy for euer. Theſe holy and heauenly Sacraments, are not effectuall in the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: <hi>Iudas,</hi> notwithſtanding he was a Diſciple of our Sauiour, and that bleſſed hand which after was nailed to the Croſſe, did reach vnto him the bread of life, yet he was ſo <hi>Hardened</hi> with ſecret ſinne,<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and a traiterous diſpoſition, that aſſone as he receiued the ſop, the diuel entereth into him, tooke full poſſeſſion of him, and ſo brought him to a moſt fearefull end. Oh happie is he that ſinneth leaſt, next he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth ſooneſt, but moſt dreadfull is the eſtate of him, who like <hi>Pharao</hi> is giuen ouer vnto <hi>Hardening.</hi> For he that is once come to this paſſe, that as <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> he hath ſold himſelfe to commit ſinne, <hi>his mind reprobate, his conſcience ſeared, and his ſoule frozen in the dregs of ſinne;</hi> then,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Tim. 4.2. <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.12.</note> though he weepe and lament with <hi>Eſau;</hi> though he would reſtore that which he hath wrongfully gotten with <hi>Iudas;</hi> though he do gird him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ſackcloth, and walk ſoftly as <hi>Ahab;</hi> though he do pull the men of God to comfort him, &amp; pray for him as <hi>Saule</hi> did; though he do mourne like a Doue, &amp;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5706:15"/>chatter like a crane, with the Pellican, though he do ſend forth ſhrill and fearefull cryes into the ayre,<note place="margin">Ier. 13.23.</note> yet all this will not helpe (wo alas) there is no recouery, <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.23. <hi>Can the blacke-Moore change his ſkinn or the Leopard his ſpotts, then may they doe good, who haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed them ſelues to do euil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. eth.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Thomas Aquin,</hi> Wiſd. 12.10. Eccus. 17.14. Hebr. 10.26. Hebr. 12.17.</note> O' <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He that Hardeneth his heart can neuer be cured. Habituati in malo ſunt impaeniturt. there thoughts can neuer be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered there ſtony hearts can not become fleſh; they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the power of ſaluation, they haue diſpited the ſpirit of grace, and though they ſeeke the bleſſings with teares they can finde no place to repentance.</hi> This is a lamentable eſtate, this is a fearefull iudgment, for man to be left vnto him ſelfe, giuen vp to ſathan, and to be forſaken of God for euer, from this eſtate the Lord for his endleſſe mercy deliuer vs. Thus haue I ſhowed how, and after what ſort men become <hi>Hardened,</hi> not of my ſelf, but as Saint <hi>Auguſtine ſaith: Ligatus teneor non fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro alteno: ſed meaferrea voluntate, velle meum tenebat ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus, et inde mihi funes fecerat, et conſuetudini dum non reſistitur facta eſt neceſſitas.</hi> A man becomes <hi>Hardened,</hi> he is fettered, not by any other chaine, but by the cordes of his owne ſinne, the deuill by deceipt gets power ouer the will, and ſo doth ſnare vs, and bicauſe in the beginning wee did not reſiſt cuſtome, at length it groweth to neceſſity. This is the very ſame in effect ſet downe by Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in the 4 to the <hi>Epheſiaus</hi> 18. where this manner of <hi>Hardening</hi> is alſo expreſſed: firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the</hi> minde is <hi>darkened,</hi> they cannot rightly diſcerne what to doe, then, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they become ignorant, thirdly comes in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> when the ſoule
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5706:15"/>(for want of heauenly dew) beginnes to <hi>whither and harde,</hi> fourthly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>paſt feeling,</hi> and laſtly giuen ouer to <hi>committ all ſinne with greedines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To eſchue this gulfe, and to auoyd the danger of this <hi>Hardening,</hi> either we muſt cut of and ſtay the courſe of ſin in the act, or elſe we muſt reſiſt it in the beginning, and ſlay it in our thoughtes. It is an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſaying of Saint <hi>Ierom: Ibi maxime oportet obſeruare pecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum, vbi naſci ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t:</hi> both in ſinne and alſo in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the diſeaſes of the body, it is the cheifeſt point, to obſerue and finde out where the malady firſt tooke beginning: it is plain, ſin firſt buddeth in the thought, and therevppon Saint <hi>Ierome calles</hi> it <hi>primo genita Diaboli,</hi> the dmills darlinge or firſt begotten. Sathan dare not attempt any vnto murther, treaſon, or any ſuch greueous ſinne; vnleſſe he ſend an euill thought before, to try whether he ſhall be welcome.</p>
            <p>The Philiſtins will not venter, till <hi>Dalilah</hi> hath wrought the feate: as ſhe with <hi>Sampſon</hi> neuer left faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and creeping into his boſome till by conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting vnto her, he loſt both his ſtrength, and his eyes, and became a mil-horſe for the <hi>Philiſtins:</hi> ſo euill thoughts they allure and toule on ſo long, till the light of the vnderſtanding being blynded, <hi>Sathan</hi> that foule Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtine ſets them ſuch a griſt to grind, as they muſt pay the loſſe of eternall life for the toule.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaid truly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Philo</note> cuſtom ariſeth of very ſmall beginnings, &amp; though it ſeeme a ſmal matter to lend the diuel an euil thought, yet thewiſeman ſaith in the 13. of <hi>Wiſd.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>Euill thoughts ſeparate from God: cogitationes malae dum ludunt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt,</hi> euil thoughts while they dally, they do deceiue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5706:16"/>As the ſtreame in the Riuer <hi>Iordan</hi> doth carry the fiſh ſwimming and playing,<note place="margin">Ioſephus.</note> till on a ſodaine they fall <hi>(in mare mortuum)</hi> into the dead ſea; where, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of brimſtone they preſently die: ſo, many ſuffer themſelues to be caried away ſo long with vicious thoughts, and wicked imaginations, that on a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, the powers of the minde be grieuouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
            <p>The eye is <hi>fenestra mentis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 9.21.</note> and many times, ere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we be aware, <hi>death ſtealeth in at the window.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eare,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 12.11.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> calleth it in his 12. Chapter: the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the ſoule: <hi>As the mouth taſteth meat for the belly: ſo the eare taſteth words for the ſoule.</hi> He that hath a wicked eye, and an vnchaſt eare (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of <hi>Simon Magus</hi>) his ſoule will ſoone be brought to the gall of bitterneſſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, wiſe men may hereby iudge, how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, how prouidently the education of youth (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially of the nobler ſort) ought to be reſpected.</p>
            <p>How flattering paraſites &amp; prophane ieſters ought to be warily ſhunned. Alas the minde and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of youth, at the firſt, it is like a ſweete and bright <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er diſh, you may put in it what you pleaſe, but if through vile <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and diſſolute company, the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection be once led away, and the diſpoſition infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, wo worth that company, for the infection of ſinne taken in tender yeares: <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſoule dieth in youth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 36.14.</note> as cloth ſtained in the wooll doth neuer loſe the colour, ſo the ſtayne of ſinne taken in tender yeares will hardly or neuer be taken out: nay, that which afterwardes diſcretion and yeares doth know
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5706:16"/>and iudge in it ſelfe moſt hateful, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by euill cuſtome,<note place="margin">Chriſoſt.</note> he is enforced to put the ſame in practiſe whether he will or no. In the 9. of <hi>Mark</hi> 21. <hi>ve.</hi> the foule ſpirit which kept poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a child, could not be caſt out by any other but onely by our Sauiour. <hi>Iob</hi> made a couenant with his heart, and <hi>Dauid</hi> prayed the Lord to turne away his eyes from beholding vanitie: euerie good man ought to labour and ſtriue with himſelfe to quench his deſires, to checke his thoughts, to beat downe and keepe vnder his affections, that though he doe ſinne ſometime of infirmity, yet it may neuer generally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the minde, it may neuer be ſetled in the thought.</p>
            <p>There is no ſacrifice more acceptable vnto God, then the nipping of a Serpents head: therefore as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh of the children of <hi>Babilon, adpetras il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidere,</hi> to daſh their braines againſt the wall, while they are young, ſo the beſt way to preuent <hi>Hardening,</hi> is to nip ſin in the head at the firſt, to kill the ſtrength of it in our thoughtes.</p>
            <p>Now, if God doe not ſo ſtrengthen vs to ouercome ſinne in the thought, the next way to ſhun this <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening</hi> is to ſtay the courſe of it in the act.<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.22.</note> 
               <hi>For God will wound the hearie ſcalpe of ſuch, as go on ſtill in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. Paruus error in principio maximus eſt in fine,</hi> A ſmall ſcape in the beginning many times proues a miſchiefe in the end. <hi>Conſuctudo peccandi tollit ſenſum peccati.</hi> The cuſtome of ſinne takes away all feeling of ſinne, as he that is ſtung with a viper, is ſo deadly benummed, that he feeles the ſting of nothing elſe, ſo he that hath taken a cuſtome of offending, neuer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5706:17"/>feels the infection of any ſinne, though it ranckle ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo grieuouſly. In the 69. Pſalm. 16. verſ. <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth, <hi>O let not the pit ſhut her mouth vpon me.</hi> To ſinne is to fal into a pit, but to take a cuſtom in ſinne, is to couer the pit and dam it vp, that we ſhall neuer get out againe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſuetudinem vincere dura pugna</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>).<note place="margin">Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in pſa: 36</note> It is a difficult fight to ouercome cuſtome, for in all humane things <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> cuſtome is the moſt intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable tyrant. <hi>Horatius</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> being to fight with three enemies at once, did ſingle them out, and then ſlue them one by one: ſo the force of ſinne is to be cut off in euery ſeuerall action, leaſt by gathering ſtrength it ouerthrow vs. <hi>He that truſteth his own heart, is not wiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28.26.</note> In this caſe, it is good for a man to ſuſpect his owne heart, to call his owne waies to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, to take ſometimes a ſuruey and a viewe of the manner of his life, and daily actions, and if he finde in himſelfe, that God hath ſuffered him ſo ſarre to be tempted, that he is fallen into any ſoule offence, which he knoweth is directly both againſt God and his owne conſcience, then preſently to beſtirre him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, neuer to ſuffer his eyes to ſleepe, nor his eyelids to ſlumber, til he haue poured out his hart vnto God, made bitter lamentation, craued pardon with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and vowed by Gods aſſiſtance neuer to offend in any ſuch ſort againe. Otherwiſe, if lightly he paſſe it ouer, and ſo go on: as <hi>Mithridates</hi> accuſtomed his bodie ſo much to the receipt of poyſon, that at length no poyſon would worke on him, ſo he that hath once taken in with the cuſtome of ſinne, ſhall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5706:17"/>at length come that to paſſe, that the greateſt ſin that is, he ſhall neuer feele it.<note place="margin">Aug. inſer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> adv. Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Owne peccatum vileſcit conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine, &amp; fit homini quaſi nullum,</hi> the greateſt ſinne by cuſtome comes to be accounted nothing. When the bodie is ſore hurt and wounded, there is no driuing off of time, but preſently it muſt be looked to; ſo when the ſoule is wounded, we muſt not deferre to turne vnto the Lord, but flie vnto him, with importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate prayer, with a broken and mourning heart, for feare, the wound doe feſter inwardly, and ſo there be no recouery. I make it plaine by example thus. If a man take in the Spring three or foure plantes, and ſet them all togither at one time, if hee come by and by, or within a while after, hee may eaſily pull vp one of them, if he ſtay a fortnight or a moneth, he may pull vp an other, but it wilbe ſomwhat harder, if he ſtay a yeare or two, till it ſettle and take roote, then he may pull and ſtraine his very heart ſtringes, but his labour is loſt he ſhall neuer be able to pull it vp. One ſinne, one offence, if we la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to pull it vpp in time, it may be forgiuen, it may be taken away; if wee lett it go on to two or three; with vnfeigned repentance, with bleedinge teares, with vnceſſant outcryes vnto a gratious God, they may be raſed out and wiped away, but with greater difficulty: at length, if a man giue ouer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto ſinne, ſo that it take deepe roote in the heart, and be ſetled in the ſoule, hee ſhall neuer be able to pull it vp, nor to ariſe from the death of ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5706:18"/>To draw then to an end: foraſmuch then, as God deſireth not the death of any ſinner, but moſt louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offereth his grace and means of ſaluation vnto all: ſeeing ſinne doth proceed from our owne vile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, and we neuer ſtriuing to ſtay the courſe of it in our thoughts, do ſo ſecretly fall away: ſeeing by degrees againſt their owne knowledge, men doe wound their ſoules with many actual ſinnes, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon God doth with-hold his grace, and ſo forſake them; and this forſaking is ſuch a forlorne eſtate, that as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith. 12.14. <hi>God ſhutteth a man vp, and he can neuer be looſed:</hi> O how feruent ought wee to bee in prayer, thereby to kindle in vs, the heat of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, how deuout in ſweet and heauenly meditations, to ſtirre vp in vs the good graces of God; how dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſhew the fruites of our faith, euer ſtirring in the works &amp; labours of our calling; giuing no aduantage to our aduerſary: how careful whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we heare the word of God, to do it with an humble ſpirit, with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, thereby to keepe a tender heart, a mind and cogitation that may eaſily be touched with remorſe, how deſirous and ſecretly ioyfull at this holy time to prepare our ſelues to the receiuing of the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, to haue our hearts ſtripped of worldly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, to call home our affections, to appeaſe our thoughts, &amp; ſo peaceably to bath our ſoules a freſh in the pretious bloud of our euerlaſting redeemer. That ſo feeling our ſelues as it were newly created againe, ſoule and bodie, heart, hand, and tongue, may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe to ſound prayſes vnto him, who doth neuer ceaſe to renewe his mereies vnto vs.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5706:18"/>The holy and kingly prophet: <hi>Dauid,</hi> he is a worthy example for this royall preſence, ſet him before your eyes, and obſerue the whole courſe of his life:</p>
            <p>How ſweete and milde was his ſpirit, in forbearing to take reuenge for him ſelfe? how couragious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible his faith, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſtood in the quarrel of Gods honour? how dearely affected to his people, when he ſaide to the deſtroying <hi>Angell,</hi> not theſe ſheepe, but it is I that haue offended? what melting &amp; kinde affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did he ſhow towards <hi>Ionathan,</hi> and thoſe whome he loued? what a mournefull and repentant heart, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he knew that he had offended, how full of diuine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to better his thoughts? how frequent in praier flowing from him as a continual ſtream? how ioyful in Gods ſeruice, dancing before the <hi>Arke?</hi> how reuerend in Gods houſe, kneeling and bowing in the temple be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the people? what a thankfull heart in offering to build a glorious temple to the <hi>Lord?</hi> what an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minde, ſaying, <hi>what am I, and what was my fathers houſe, that thou haſt brought vs hitherto?</hi> what a chary &amp; tender care of Gods glory wherſoeuer he became? how abundant in prayſes and thankſgiuing, calling euery member of himſelfe, and all the creatures both of heauen and earth to make one quier in ſetting forth, ſinging, and ſounding the euerlaſting prayſes of his God? but why did <hi>Dauid</hi> thus? to what end was al this? that he might be ſure ſtill <hi>to hould faſt by God,</hi> to be entirely knitt vnto him, by all meanes poſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his loue; for feare, leaſt God hauing rayſed him to the height of renowne, deliuered him miracolouſly out of many eminent and bloudy daungers, and ſo ſet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5706:19"/>a crowne of bleſſings vpon his heade: if <hi>Deuid</hi> ſhould haue ſhowen any vnthankfullnes, any contempt, or the leaſt neglect of his loue a mighty and ielous God, he alſo, vpon iuſt cauſe might haue withdrawne his loue, and laide all his honour in the duſt againe.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, with all humbleneſſe and duety I entreate you by the tender mercyes of Chriſt Ieſus, and in the name of the liuing God I challenge euery Chriſtian which hopes for any ioy in the life to come, take heede of actuall and preſumptuous ſinnes, in no caſe let them <hi>haue dominion cuer you,</hi> doe not wound your ſoules (as <hi>Pharao</hi> did) with willfull offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your owne knowledge, try and examine all your thoughts, how and wherein they ſtand affected, and aboue all, greiue not the bleſſed motions of that comfortable ſpirit, which keepes the very <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Beeing</hi> of the ſoule. To conclude, let all ſlaunderous mouthes be ſtopped, and all the factious ſciſmatiques in the land aſhamed, in beholding your Chriſtian and princely example: continew ſtill to be louingly and kindly affected one towards another: celebrate this holy time in a true religious manner: Sanctifie the ioyfull beginninge of this new yeares raigne with new deuotion vnto God: lay all your <hi>Honours</hi> downe at the foote of the <hi>altar:</hi> Receiue the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments ioyntly together, and ſo be faithfully knitt in loue and in one head <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> go cheerefully on, delight ſtill in doing good: and the <hi>Lord God</hi> of our fathers encreaſe in you good deſires, giue you zeale to performe them, confirme vnto you, and to your ſeede all his good promiſes, and vnto euery
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5706:19"/>one of vs heere grant pardon for offences paſt, giue vs comfort and ſtrength in temptations to come, euen for his bleſſed Sonne <hi>Chriſt Ieſus ſake:</hi> who with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be bleſſed and prayſed for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
